Guide to the Max Gordon: Communist Party, USA Crisis of 1956-1958: Internal Documents Collection TAM.519
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Max Gordon Communist Party, USA Internal Documents Collection
circa 1956-1958
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gordon, Max, 1920-1990
Gordon, Nicholas
TAM.519
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Max Gordon (1910-1990) was the (New York) City Editor of the Communist Pary USA's newspaper, the Daily Worker who sided with the unsuccessful social democratic reform faction during the 1956-1958 internal Party struggle in the aftermath of the famous "secret" speech in April 1956 by Nikita Khrushchev denouncing Stalin at the twentieth congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union. This small collection consists of internal policy statements official and unofficial, by local and nationalParty bodies or by leading members.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Nicholas Gordon in 1984. The accession number associated with this gift is 2009.089.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into one alphabetically arranged series.
Historical/Biographical Note
Max Gordon (1910-1990) was the (New York) City Editor of the Communist Pary USA's newspaper, the Daily Worker who sided with the unsuccessful social democratic reform faction during the Party's 1956-1958 internal struggle in the aftermath of the famous "secret" speech in April 1956 by Nikita Khrushchev denouncing Stalin at the twentieth congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union. He was born in Gloversville, N.Y., graduated from City College, was an organizer for the Party in the Albany, N.Y. area before joining the editorial staff of the Daily Worker in 1942.
Provenance
Gift of Nicholas Gordon (son), September 17, 1984
Scope and Contents
This small collection consists of internal policy statements official and unofficial, by local and nationalParty bodies or by leading members. Notable individuals represented include A.B. Magil (on Yugoslavia) and James Jackson (on issues pertaining to African Americans). There are also documents from the Ohio Party organization and from a group of members of the Party's the Southern California District, and a press release issued in response to the 1958 resignation of Daily Worker editor John Gates.
Jewish communists -- United States.; Reports.; African American communists.; Communism -- United States.; Strack, Celeste; Communist Party of the United States of America (Ohio); Communist Party of the United States of America. Southern California District; Magil, A. B. (Abraham Bernard), 1905-2003; Jackson, James E., 1914-2007; Communist Party of the United States of America; Gordon, Nicholas
- Collection (Box 1)
  - Communist Party National Administrative Committee: Press Release on the Resignation of John Gates, Jan 10, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party National Administrative Committee: "To All Members of the National Committee", Dec 3, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Draft Labor Policy [Unsigned], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fund Drive [New York State Report], Jul 3, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jackson, James E. "Certain Concepts Towards a Resolution on the C.P. and the Negro Question." (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jackson, James E. "C.P. Position or Status and Prospects of the "Black Belt"", ca. 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Magil, A.B. "The Yugoslav Question.", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Memorandum on Negro History Week.. ." / New York State Communist Party Educational Department, ca. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York State [Communist Party] Committee Documents, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report of the Ohio State Board to the State Committee, Nov 11, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Strack, Celeste. Letter to the National Committee from Members of the Southern California C.P. District [with a cover letter to Max Gordon], 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Toward Establishing the Basis for a Program in Culture" / by P.B., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)